A Guide to the Andrew Reid Venable Papers, 1862
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Andrew Reid Venable Papers, 1862
The Library of Virginia
22231
.25 cubic feet
Andrew Reid Venable
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mrs. Reid Venable, Richmond, Virginia, 30 March 1944.
Biographical Information
Andrew Reid Venable was born 2 December 1832 at Vineyard in Prince Edward County, Virginia, to Samuel Woodson Venable (1797-1855) and Jane Reid Venable. He graduated from Hampden-Sydney in 1852 and travelled west. Venable settled in St. Louis, Missouri, and became a successful businessman. There he met an army officer named Jeb Stuart (1833-1864) and the two became good friends. He also met Adeline Hackney Stevens, niece of the governor of Maryland and his future wife. When the Civil War began, Venable returned to Virginia and joined the Richmond Howitzers, serving in action. In the summer of 1862, he was appointed captain and assistant commissary of subsistence for the 1st Regiment, Virginia Artillery. After the battle of Chancellorsville, Venable was promoted to major and transferred to Stuart's staff as assistant adjutant and inspector-general of the cavalry corps. He served on Stuart's staff until the latter's death 11 May 1864. Venable then served on the staff of General Wade Hampton who succeeded Stuart commanding the cavalry corps. Venable was captured at the battle of Hatcher's Run 27 October 1864. Being transferred from Old Capitol prison in Washington D.C. to Fort Delaware, Venable made his escape near Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. Southern sympathizers in Philadelphia hid him. Adeline Stevens met him in Philadelphia, and the two were married. Venable returned south and served until the end of the war. After the war, he returned to Prince Edward County and farmed. He and his wife had six children. Venable died 15 October 1909 at Millwood in Prince Edward County.
Scope and Content
Papers, July-December 1862, of Andrew Reid Venable (1832-1909), captain and assistant commissary of subsistence, 1st Regiment, Virginia Artillery, Confederate Army, consisting of absracts, accounts, invoices, receipts, reports, returns, statements, and vouchers relevant to his duties and responsibilities as commissary officer.
Contents List
- Abstract of disbursements on Account of Contingencies...for the quarter ending 31 December 1862. (Folder 1)
- Abstracts of Extra Issues to Troops in the Field..., July, August, and September 1862. (Folder 2)
- Abstracts of Provisions Issued, July-December 1862. (Folder 3)
- Abstracts of Provisions Sold to Officers..., July-December 1862. Items noted as Form 5. (Folder 4)
- Abstracts of Purchases Made on Account of the Subsistence of the Army..., September-December 1862. Items noted as Form 8. (Folder 5)
- Confederate States of America on Account of Army Subsistence in the Quarter Ending 31 December 1862. Item noted as Form 7. (Folder 6)
- Confederate States to Hamilton Light, S. F. Jones, A. J. Ridgway, and John W. Turner for provisions, September, October, and December 1862. Items noted as Form 19. (Folder 7)
- Consolidated Abstract of Provisions Sold to Officers...for the Quarter Ending 30 September and 31 December 1862. Items noted as Form 10. (Folder 8)
- Consolidated Provision Returns..., July-December 1862. Items noted as Form 14. (Folder 9)
- District Abstract of Other Sales during the Quarter Ending 31 December 1862. (Folder 10)
- Invoice of Subsistence Stores (Provisions) Delivered..., July-December 1862. Items noted as Form 22. (Folder 11)
- Monthly Summary Statement of Funds Received and Disbursed..., July-December 1862. (Folder 12)
- Provision Returns for Two Detachments on Picket near Charlestown..., 2-20 October 1862. (Folder 13)
- Received at Camp near Richmond, 13 August 1862. This item noted as Form 24. (Folder 14)
- Return of Provisions Received and Issued in the Field..., July-December 1862. (Folder 15)
- Appointment and Reports of Boards Relevant to Condition of Commissary Provisions, July-September, November 1862. (Folder 16)
- Receipts, Vouchers, etc., July 1862. (Folder 17)
- Receipts, Vouchers, etc., August 1862. (Folder 18)
- Receipts, Vouchers, etc., September 1862. (Folder 19)
- Receipts, Vouchers, etc., October 1862. (Folder 20)
- Receipts, Vouchers, etc., November 1862. (Folder 21)
- Receipts, Vouchers, etc., December 1862.